<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The deplorable state and condition of the poor French Protestants commiserated, and humbly represented to all princes and people of the true reformed church with reasons for a Protestant league.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35705</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1076</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11774616</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11774616</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48929</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35705)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48929)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 488:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The deplorable state and condition of the poor French Protestants commiserated, and humbly represented to all princes and people of the true reformed church with reasons for a Protestant league.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Janeway,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestants --  France.</term>
               <term>Huguenots --  France.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48929:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Deplorable State AND CONDITION Of the POOR <hi>French Proteſtants</hi> COMMISERATED, And humbly Repreſented to all <hi>Princes and People</hi> Of the TRUE Reformed Church; With Reaſons for a Proteſtant League.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Janeway</hi> in <hi>Queens-Head-Alley</hi> in <hi>Pater-Noſter-Row,</hi> MDCLXXXI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:48929:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48929:2"/>
            <head>The Deplorable State and Condition of the Poor <hi>French Proteſtants</hi> Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>NO ſooner have theſe <hi>Popiſh Hornets,</hi> their <hi>Prieſts,</hi> been Expel'd and Fired out of any <hi>Kingdom</hi> or <hi>Countrey,</hi> but like the fallen Angels, They uſe all means and endeavours to recover again their loſt <hi>Dominions;</hi> and accordingly leave no expedient unattempted, whereby they might draw over the moſt Powerful Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to their Party: With the <hi>Emperour,</hi> the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and others of weak <hi>Judgments,</hi> they make a <hi>Religious</hi> account only, and the Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Catholick Cauſe,</hi> to be a ſufficient ground for their aſſiſtance, or at leaſt to prevent their interruption of thoſe more Vigorous Princes, who help to carry on their Deſigns: With the <hi>French King,</hi> and others of more refined Politicks, abandoning all motives of Religion, they uſe the Perſwaſives of ſome temporal. Intereſt, engaging to aſſiſt him in the Deſign of his Univerſal Monarchy; if he will as mutually promote their Univerſal <hi>Hierarchy</hi> and the extirpation of <hi>Hereſie;</hi> Thus, as the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> have given him many Taſtes of their ſervices in a Politick way: So now they think it high time that his moſt <hi>Chriſtian Majeſty</hi> ſhould preſent them with ſome Teſtimony of his Zeal for the <hi>Church</hi> ſervice: And as in order to his Univerſal Monarchy, they have divided the <hi>Engliſh</hi> with <hi>Plots,</hi> bred <hi>Jealouſies</hi> between the <hi>States</hi> and <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> by the <hi>Lovai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten Faction,</hi> exaſperated and divided the <hi>Emperour</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> of the <hi>Empire</hi> one againſt another, and <hi>Betrayed</hi> the <hi>Counſels</hi> of all other <hi>Courts</hi> to the <hi>French;</hi> So now in requital for all theſe Eminent <hi>State-ſervices,</hi> His <hi>Majeſty</hi> (though Impartial to all <hi>Religious</hi> in His Judgement) yet on a Politick ſcore, hath thus begun the Extirpation of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> by this Barbarous Invaſion of the Lives of ſome, but Fortunes and Children of all his moſt Loyal (though <hi>Proteſtant</hi>) Subjects. From hence it more plainly appears, that the <hi>Plot</hi> for Introducing <hi>Popery</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> was but one ſmall part of their Deſigns, who undoubtedly intended an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Extirpation of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> out of all parts of the World: Wherefore this is the time that all <hi>Proteſtant Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> ought Firmly and Unanimouſly to <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Confederate</hi> with the ſame zeal againſt the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and their <hi>falſe Religion,</hi> as They do againſt the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> and the true <hi>Worſhip of God;</hi> Whereto we are oblig'd, both by the Law of <hi>God,</hi> Law of <hi>Nature,</hi> and Law of <hi>Nations;</hi> as appears by many <hi>Preſidents,</hi> as well <hi>Sacred</hi> as <hi>Prophane,</hi> which I ſhall here produce in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of theſe diſtreſſed and miſerable People, who by this <hi>Jeſuitical Hector</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> are reduced even to the extremity of <hi>Want</hi> and <hi>Miſery,</hi> expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every hour in the Night to be <hi>Allarm'd</hi> with another St. <hi>Bartholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mew</hi>'s <hi>Maſſacre;</hi> who like <hi>Herod Butchering</hi> the <hi>Innocents,</hi> may ſerve to <hi>Warn all other</hi> Proteſtant Subjects <hi>what quarter they are like to meet with under a</hi> Popiſh King.</p>
            <p>There are many <hi>Princes,</hi> who hoping to advance their own ends, and encroach on others Rights, will rightly embrace the part of the afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and proclaim the Lawfulneſs of it; but the hope of gain is the certain and only aim of their procecedings: Thus the <hi>Romans, Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the <hi>great,</hi> and divers others, pretending to ſuppreſs <hi>Tyrants,</hi> have oftentimes enlarged their own <hi>Territories.</hi> It is not long ſince <hi>Henry</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:48929:3"/>the ſecond of <hi>France</hi> made <hi>Wars</hi> upon the <hi>Emperour Charles</hi> the firſt, under Colour of defending and delivering the <hi>Proteſtant Princes.</hi> As alſo <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> was in like manner ready to aſſiſt the <hi>Germans,</hi> if the <hi>Emperour Charles</hi> ſhould moleſt them. But if there be ſome appearance of Danger, and little expectance of Profit, then it is that moſt Princes diſpute the Lawfulneſs of the Action. And as the former cover their Ambition and Avarice with the evil of <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Piety:</hi> So on the contrary, do the others call their fear and Cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, Integrity and Juſtice. Therefore without leaning either to the one ſide or the other, let us Impartially examine thoſe rules in ſuch caſes which <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> trace us out in matter of <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, All accord in this, <hi>That there is one only Church, whereof</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>is the Head;</hi> the members whereof are ſo united and conjoyned together, that if the leaſt of them be offended or wronged, they all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate both in Harm and Sorrow, as throughout the <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> plainly appears. Wherefore the <hi>Church</hi> is compared to a <hi>Body:</hi> Now it many tims happens that the <hi>Body</hi> is not only overthrown by a Wound in the Arm, or Thigh, but alſo ſometimes endanger'd and killed even by a ſmall hurt in the little Finger; Vainly therefore doth any Man boaſt of the ſafe cuſtody of his <hi>Body,</hi> if he ſuffers that to be Diſmembred and Pulled in pieces, which he might have preſerved whole and entire. The <hi>Church</hi> alſo is compared to an <hi>Edifice:</hi> on which ſide ſoever the Building is undermined, it often happens that the whole tumbles down; and on what Rafter or piece of Timber ſoever the Flame takes hold, it endangers the whole Houſe of Burning; He muſt needs be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore very ridiculous, who ſhould defer to quench the Fire which had ſeized on his Houſe-top, becauſe he dwells moſt in the Celler. Again, the <hi>Church</hi> is reſembled to a <hi>Ship,</hi> which as it Sails together, ſo doth it Sink together: inſomuch that in a tempeſt, thoſe who be in the <hi>Fore-caſtle,</hi> or in the <hi>Keel,</hi> are no more ſecure, then thoſe who remain at the <hi>Stearn</hi> or on the <hi>Lower Deck;</hi> they both venture in one Bottom. This being granted, queſtionleſs, whoſoever hath not a fellow-feeling in Commiſerating the Trouble, Danger, and Diſtreſs of the <hi>Church,</hi> is no Member of that <hi>Body,</hi> nor <hi>Domeſtick</hi> in the <hi>Family</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> nor hath any place in the <hi>Ark</hi> of the <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Grace.</hi> He who hath any ſenſe of <hi>Religion</hi> in his heart, ought no more to doubt, whether he be obliged to aid the afflicted <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> than whether he would be aſſiſting to himſelf in the like diſtreſs: for the Union of the <hi>Church</hi> Unites us all into one <hi>Body,</hi> and therefore every one in his calling muſt be ready to aſſiſt the Needy.</p>
            <p>Now as this <hi>Church</hi> is one, ſo is ſhe recommended and given in charge to all <hi>Chriſtian Princes</hi> in general, and to every one of them in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar: for in as much as it was dangerous to leave the care to one alone, and the Unity of it would not by any means permit that ſhe ſhould be divided into pieces, and every portion aſſigned unto one particular: God hath Committed it all entire to particulars, and all the parts of it to all in general, not only to preſerve and defend it, but alſo to am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifie and increaſe it as much as might be: inſomuch, that if a <hi>Prince</hi> who hath undertaken the care of a portion of the <hi>Church,</hi> (as that of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> and <hi>Holland.</hi>) doth notwithſtanding neglect and forſake another part that is oppreſſed, and which he might ſuccour; He doubtleſs aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons the <hi>Church, Chriſt</hi> having but one only <hi>Spouſe,</hi> which the <hi>Prince</hi> is ſo bound to preſerve and defend, that ſhe be not violated or corrupted in any part, if it be poſſible. And in the ſame manner as every private
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48929:3"/>Perſon is bound by his <hi>Humble</hi> and <hi>Ardent Prayers to God,</hi> to deſire the <hi>Reſtoring of the Church:</hi> So likewiſe are the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> tyed diligently to procure the ſame with the utmoſt of that <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Means</hi> which <hi>God</hi> hath put into their Hands. Now it were ridiculous and worthy of Puniſhment in the <hi>Church wardens,</hi> who had care only of ſome ſmall part of the <hi>Church,</hi> and ſuffer'd all the reſt to be ſpoil'd with Rain and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: In like manner, all <hi>Chriſtian Kings</hi> when they receive the <hi>Sword</hi> on the day of their <hi>Coronation,</hi> ſolemnly <hi>Swear, to maintain the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church,</hi> and the <hi>Ceremony</hi> then uſed doth fully expreſs it; for holding the <hi>Sword</hi> in their hands, they turning to the <hi>Eaſt, Weſt, North,</hi> and <hi>South, Brandiſh</hi> it, to the end that it may be known, that no part of the <hi>World</hi> is excepted. And that this was accordingly the Practice of <hi>Ancient Princes,</hi> we have their Examples to inſtruct us.</p>
            <p>In the time of <hi>Ezechias</hi> King of <hi>Juda,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 30.</note> the Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had been a long time before in Subjection to the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> to wit, ever ſince the King <hi>Oſea</hi>'s time: And therefore if the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Juda</hi> only, and not the whole <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church</hi> had been committed to the Cuſtody of <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias:</hi> and if in the preſervation of the <hi>Church</hi> the ſame courſe were to be held, as in the dividing of Lands, or impoſing of <hi>Tributes,</hi> then queſtionleſs <hi>Ezechias</hi> would have contained himſelf within his own Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, eſpecially when the <hi>Exhorbitant Power</hi> of the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> Lorded it every where. Now we read that he ſent expreſs Meſſengers throughout <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to wit, to the Subjects of the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> to invite them to come to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to celebrate the <hi>Paſchal Feaſt:</hi> and moreover he aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the faithful <hi>Iſraelites</hi> of the <hi>Tribes</hi> of <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> and others the Subjects of the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> to ruin the <hi>High Places</hi> which were in their <hi>Quarters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We read alſo that the good <hi>King Joſias</hi> expell'd <hi>Idolatry,</hi> not only out of his own Kingdom, but alſo even out of the Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kin. 22. 2 Chro. 22. and 35.</note> which was then wholly in ſubjection to the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Aſſyria.</hi> And no wonder is it, for where the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and Kingdom of <hi>Chriſt</hi> are in queſtion, certainly no Bounds or Limits ſhould there confine the zeal and fervent Affection of <hi>Pious</hi> and <hi>Godly Princes.</hi> Though the Oppoſition be great, and power of the Oppoſers greater, yet the more they fear <hi>God,</hi> the leſs will they fear Men. Theſe generous Examples of the aforeſaid <hi>Godly Princes</hi> have ſince been imitated by ſundry <hi>Chriſtian Kings,</hi> by whoſe means the <hi>Church</hi> (which was heretofore reſtrain'd within the narrow Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of <hi>Paleſtine,</hi>) hath ſince been dilated throughout moſt part of the Univerſe. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> and <hi>Licinius</hi> Govern'd the <hi>Empire</hi> together, one in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> the other in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> they were <hi>Aſſociates</hi> of equal Power and Authority; Nevertheleſs, for as much as <hi>Licinius</hi> doth every where <hi>Baniſh, Torment,</hi> and put to <hi>Death</hi> the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> under pretence of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: Conſtantine</hi> makes <hi>War</hi> againſt him, and by force compels him to give free <hi>Toleration</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> to the <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and becauſe afterwards he broke his Faith, and relapſed into his former <hi>Cruelties</hi> againſt them: <hi>Conſtantine</hi> cauſed him to be <hi>Apprehended</hi> and put to <hi>Death</hi> in the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>Theſſalonica.</hi> Which <hi>Pious</hi> Action of this <hi>Emperours</hi> was with ſo great an <hi>Applauſe Celebrated</hi> by the <hi>Divines</hi> of thoſe times, that they ſuppoſe that ſaying of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> to be meant by him, <hi>that Kings ſhould be Paſtors and Nurſing Fathers of the Church.</hi> Again, after <hi>Conſtantines Death,</hi> the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> was divided equally between his Sons, without any Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority or Advantage one more than the other. <hi>Conſtance</hi> the Younger favour'd the <hi>Orthordex Chriſtians,</hi> and <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the Elder enclined to the <hi>Arrians;</hi> for which reaſon he Baniſhed the Learned <hi>Athanaſius</hi> from <hi>Alexandria,</hi> as being the greateſt profeſſed Adverſary of the <hi>Arrians.</hi> Here, if any Conſideration in matter of <hi>Conſcience</hi> were abſolutely requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48929:4"/>it would certainly be amongſt Brethren. But nevertheleſs, <hi>Conſtance</hi> threatens to wage <hi>War</hi> on his Brother, if he reſtore not <hi>Athanaſius;</hi> and had undoubtedly performed it, if <hi>Conſtantius</hi> had not readily Complied with his deſire. Now, if he proceeded ſo far for the <hi>Reſtauration</hi> of one ſingle <hi>Biſhop:</hi> had there not been much more reaſon for him to have aſſiſted a great part of the People, if they ſhould have implored his Aid againſt the <hi>Tyranny</hi> of <hi>Wicked Princes,</hi> who refuſe them to exerciſe the only <hi>True Worſhip of God?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sozom.</hi> lib. 7. Ch. 18.</note> In like manner, at the Perſwaſion of <hi>Atticus</hi> the <hi>Biſhop, Theodoſius</hi> made <hi>War</hi> upon <hi>Coſroes King</hi> of <hi>Perſia,</hi> to force him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of his Kingdom from <hi>Perſecution,</hi> although they were but particular and private Perſons: which certainly thoſe moſt <hi>Juſt Princes,</hi> who inſtituted ſo many <hi>worthy Laws,</hi> and had ſo great a regard to <hi>Juſtice,</hi> would never have done, if by ſo doing they had conceived any thing were <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurped</hi> on another Mans right, or the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nations violated.</hi> But to what end were ſo many <hi>Expeditions</hi> undertaken by <hi>Chriſtian Princes,</hi> into the <hi>Holy Land</hi> againſt the <hi>Sarracens?</hi> Wherefore were demanded and raiſed ſo many of thoſe <hi>Saladine Tenths?</hi> To what purpoſe were ſo many <hi>Confederacies</hi> made, and <hi>Croyſadoes</hi> Proclaimed againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> if it were not lawful for <hi>Chriſtian Princes,</hi> yea thoſe fartheſt remote, to deliver the <hi>Church of God</hi> from the <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants,</hi> and to free <hi>Captive Chriſtians</hi> from under the <hi>Yoke of Bondage?</hi> What were the Motives that led them to thoſe <hi>Wars?</hi> And what were the Reaſons that urged them to undergo thoſe <hi>Dangers,</hi> but only their care of the <hi>Church <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion? Chriſt</hi> Summoned every Man from all parts to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake the defence thereof. All Men are bound to repel <hi>Common dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> with a <hi>joynt</hi> and <hi>Common Oppoſition:</hi> which hath a <hi>natural Conſent</hi> and <hi>Relation</hi> with what we now treat of: For if this were lawful in them againſt <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and not only lawful, but that the backward and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligenti were ever made liable to all <hi>Infamous contempts,</hi> and the forward <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakers</hi> always <hi>recompenced</hi> with all <hi>Honourable reſpect</hi> and <hi>reward,</hi> according to the merit of their <hi>Vertues:</hi> Wherefore not now againſt the <hi>Enemy</hi> to <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs?</hi> If it be a lawful <hi>War</hi> to <hi>fight</hi> againſt the <hi>Greeks,</hi> when they <hi>Aſſail</hi> our <hi>Troy;</hi> wherefore is it unlawful to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue and prevent that <hi>Incendiary Lewis</hi> the <hi>Fourteenth,</hi> who hath ſet all the <hi>European World</hi> in a <hi>Flame,</hi> for no other reaſon but <hi>pour ſa Gloire?</hi> Do we pray <hi>God</hi> to abate a <hi>Peſtilence,</hi> and to take away a <hi>Famine?</hi> why ſhould we not in the ſame manner Pray againſt that <hi>Prince</hi> who is ſent inſtead of both; Who hath <hi>deſtroyed</hi> more Men than either the one or the other, nay then both together? And why may we not as well flie to our <hi>Force</hi> and <hi>Arms</hi> for the one, as to our <hi>Drugs</hi> and <hi>Phyſick</hi> for the other? Finally, If it hath been eſteem'd an <hi>Heroical Act,</hi> to deliver <hi>Chriſtians</hi> from <hi>Corporal ſervitude,</hi> (for the <hi>Turks</hi> compel none in point of <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>) why is it not a thing much more noble, to <hi>Infranchiſe</hi> and ſet at <hi>Liberty</hi> theſe <hi>diſtreſſed</hi> and <hi>vertuous French Proteſtants,</hi> from the <hi>Chains</hi> and <hi>Tyranny</hi> of <hi>Popery;</hi> which as it is moſt <hi>Foppiſh</hi> in its <hi>Doctrine,</hi> ſo is it moſt <hi>Bloudy</hi> in its <hi>Teneuts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now theſe examples of ſo many <hi>Religious Princes,</hi> might well have the directive power of Law. Nevertheleſs, let us hear what <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Pronounces in many places of his Word, by the Mouth of his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> againſt thoſe who advance not the <hi>Building up</hi> of his <hi>Church,</hi> or who make no reckoning of her afflictions. The <hi>Gadites,</hi> the <hi>Rubenites,</hi> and half Tribe of <hi>Manaſſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 32, Joſh. 4.12. Deu. 3 20.</note> deſire of <hi>Moſes,</hi> That he would allot them their Portion on the other ſide of <hi>Jordan. Moſes</hi> grants their requeſt, but with this <hi>Proviſo</hi> and <hi>Condition:</hi> That they ſhould not only aſſiſt their other <hi>Brethren</hi> the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to <hi>Conquer</hi> the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> but alſo that they ſhould March the firſt, and ſerve as <hi>Vant-guard</hi> to the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48929:4"/>reſt, becauſe they had their Portions firſt ſet them forth; And if they fail to perform this duty, he with an <hi>Anathema,</hi> deſtines them to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and compares them to thoſe who were adjudged <hi>Rebels</hi> at <hi>Cadizbarnea. And what?</hi> (ſaid he,) <hi>Your Brethren Fight, and you in the mean while reſt quiet at home? No, on the contrary, You alſo ſhall paſs</hi> Jordan, <hi>and not return into your Houſes, before the Lord hath firſt driven his Enemies out from before his face, and given place to your Brethren as well as you, then ſhall you be Innocent before the Lord and his People</hi> Iſrael. By this he ſhews, that thoſe whom <hi>God</hi> firſt bleſſed with ſo great a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, if they help not their Brethren, and make not themſelves ſharers in their Travels, Companions in their Labours, and Leaders in their Dangers, muſt queſtionleſs expect an heavy Judgment to fall upon them.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe, when under the Conduct of <hi>Debora,</hi> the <hi>Nephtalites</hi> and <hi>Zabulonites</hi> took Arms againſt the <hi>Tyrant Jabin:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judges 5.</note> and that in the mean while the <hi>Rubenites</hi> who ſhould have been firſt in the field, took their eaſe, and played on their Pipes, whilſt their Flocks and Herds fed at liberty: The <hi>Gadites</hi> held themſelves ſecure with the <hi>Rampire</hi> of the <hi>River:</hi> The <hi>Danites</hi> gloried in their Naval Force; And, to be brief, <hi>Aſhur</hi> was confident in the difficult Acceſs of their Mountains: Then the Spirt of the Lord ſpeaking by the <hi>Propheteſs,</hi> doth condemn them all in theſe terms, <hi>Curſe ye</hi> Meroz, (ſaid the <hi>Angel</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jud. 5.23.</note>) <hi>curſe ye bitterly the Inhabitants thereof: becauſe they came not to the help of the Lord, to the help of the Lord againſt the mighty:</hi> But bleſſed above Woman ſhall <hi>Jael</hi> the Wife of <hi>Heber</hi> the <hi>Kenito</hi> be, who though ſhe might have alledged her Husbands Alliance with the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> did not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding kill <hi>Siſera</hi> the <hi>General</hi> of the Enemies Army. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi> ſpake Reilgiouſly and like a true <hi>Patriarch</hi> when he ſaid,<note place="margin">2 Sa. 11.11</note> 
               <hi>The Ark of the Lord, and</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and</hi> Judah, <hi>abide in Tents, and my Lord</hi> Joab, <hi>and the ſervants of my Lord are Encamped in the open Field; Shall I then go into my houſe, to Eat, Drink, and lie with my Wife? As thou liveſt, and as thy Soul liveth, I will not do this thing.</hi> But on the contrary, impious and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed were the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who ſuppoſing themſelves ſecure by the <hi>craggy Mountains</hi> of <hi>Samaria,</hi> and ſtrong Fortifications of <hi>Sion,</hi> took liberty to loſe themſelves in <hi>Luxurious Feaſts,</hi> looſe delights,<note place="margin">Amos 6.</note> Drinking Delicious Wines, and Sleeping in <hi>Perfumed Beds</hi> of <hi>Ivory,</hi> in the mean time deſpiſing poor <hi>Joſeph,</hi> to wit, the <hi>Lords Flock,</hi> tormented, and miſerably vext on all ſides, not having any Compaſſion on their affliction.<note place="margin">Jud. 8.12.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord God hath ſworn by himſelf, ſaith the Lord God of</hi> Hoſts, <hi>I abhor the Excellency of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and hate his Palaces: Therefore will I deliver up the City, with all that is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; and thoſe that wallow thus in pleaſure, ſhall be the firſt that ſhall go into Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity.</hi> Wickedly therefore did thoſe <hi>Ephraimites,</hi> who inſtead of Congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulating and Applauding the famous Victories of <hi>Gideon</hi> and <hi>Jeptha,</hi> did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and traduce them, whom notwithſtanding they had forſaken in dangers.</p>
            <p>As much may be ſaid of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who ſeeing <hi>David</hi> overcome the difficulty of his Affairs, and remain a peaceable King, ſay aloud,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>We are thy Fleſh and thy Bones:</hi> But ſome years after, ſeeing him again Embroiled in Troubles, cryed out, <hi>We have no part in</hi> David,<note place="margin">2 Sa. 20.1.</note> 
               <hi>neither have we Inheritance in the ſon of</hi> Jeſſe. Let us rank alſo with theſe, all thoſe <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in Name only, who will <hi>communicate</hi> at the <hi>Holy Table,</hi> and yet refuſe to <hi>Participate</hi> of the <hi>Cup</hi> of <hi>affliction</hi> with their <hi>Brethren;</hi> who look for ſalvation in the <hi>Church,</hi> yet care not for the ſafety and preſervation of the ſaid <hi>Church,</hi> and the <hi>Members</hi> thereof; Briefly, who adore one and the ſame <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Father,</hi> acknowledge and avow themſelves of the ſame <hi>Houſhold</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> and profeſs to be one and the ſame <hi>Body</hi> in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yield no ſuccour nor aſſiſtance to their <hi>Saviour</hi> afflicted in his <hi>Members.</hi> What revenge do you think will <hi>God</hi> inflict on ſuch Impiety? <hi>Moſes</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48929:5"/>thoſe who abandon their <hi>Brethren</hi> to the <hi>Rebels</hi> of <hi>Cadesbarnea:</hi> Now none of thoſe by the <hi>Decree</hi> of the <hi>Almighty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 32.</note> entered into the land of <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an:</hi> Let not ſuch then pretend to any intereſt in the <hi>Heavenly Canaan,</hi> who will not Succour <hi>Chriſt</hi> when he is <hi>Crucified,</hi> and ſuffering a thouſand times a day in his <hi>Members,</hi> as it were begging their <hi>Almes</hi> from door to door. The <hi>Son of God</hi> with his own mouth condemns them to everlaſting Fire, that <hi>when he was hungry, gave him no Meat, when he was thirſty, gave him no Drink, when he was a ſtranger, Lodged him not; naked, and Cloathed him not; ſick and in Priſon, yet Viſited him not.</hi> Wherefore let thoſe expect puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without end, who lend a deaf Ear to the <hi>Complaints</hi> and <hi>Groans</hi> of our <hi>Saviour Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> ſuffering all theſe things daily in his <hi>Church;</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though otherwiſe they may appear both to themſelves and others to be good Chriſtians, yet ſhall their condition be much more Miſerable then that of many <hi>Infidels:</hi> For why, were they only the <hi>Jews,</hi> or <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> that perſecuted <hi>Chriſt?</hi> or were they <hi>Ethnicks</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> which thus perſecute, torment, and Crucify him? No certainly, the <hi>Jews</hi> hold him an <hi>Impoſtor,</hi> the <hi>Ethnicks</hi> a <hi>Malefactor,</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> an <hi>Infidel;</hi> Inſomuch as if we conſider the Intention of theſe Men, (as the cenſuring of all offences ought to have principal Relation thereunto,) we cannot conclude that it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly <hi>Chriſt</hi> that they <hi>perſecute</hi> with ſuch hatred, but rather ſome Criminal Perſon, whom in their opinion deſerves this uſage: Whereas they do truly and more properly perſecute and Crucify afreſh <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> who profeſſing to acknowledge him for the <hi>Meſſias, God</hi> and <hi>Redeemer</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> do yet notwithſtanding fail to free him from <hi>Perſecution</hi> and <hi>Vexation</hi> in his <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> when it is in their power to do it. Briefly, He who omits to deliver his <hi>Neighbour</hi> from the hands of the <hi>Murderer,</hi> when it is in his power to do it, is little leſs guilty of the <hi>Murther</hi> before <hi>God,</hi> then the <hi>Murtherer</hi> himſelf: <hi>Qui non prohibet cum poteſt, Jubet.</hi> Nay, I may ſay farther, that theſe <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerters</hi> of their <hi>Brethren</hi> in their time of Danger and Diſtreſs, are more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious and guilty, than the <hi>Tyrants</hi> themſelves that Perſecute them: for it is much more wicked and worthy of greater puniſhment to kill an honeſt Man that is Innocent and fearing <hi>God,</hi> (as thoſe who conſent with them in their Faith muſt of neceſſity know their true profeſſion to be,) then to kill a Thief, Impoſtor, or Heretick; (as thoſe who perſecute the true <hi>Chriſtian Proteſtants</hi> do commonly believe them to be,) It is a greater offence to ſtrive with <hi>God</hi> then Man; Finally, it is a far greater Crime perfidiouſly to betray, then ignorantly to off end. The ſame may alſo be ſaid of them who refuſe to aſſiſt the true <hi>Servants of God,</hi> when oppreſſed by <hi>Tyranny</hi> for <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion's ſake:</hi> We ought to love our Neighbours as our ſelves; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> is not only bound to deliver an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> from the hands of <hi>Thieves,</hi> if it be in his power, but every <hi>Stranger</hi> alſo; yea, though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, if he will rightly diſcharge his duty: Neither let him diſpute, whether it be lawful to defend another, who believes he may juſtly defend himſelf; for it is more juſt and generous (if we rightly conſider it) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver from danger and outrage another than ones ſelf; ſeeing that what is done for pure <hi>Charity,</hi> is more commendable and praiſe-worthy, then that which is done out of <hi>ſelf ends, deſire of Revenge,</hi> or any other <hi>tranſport of Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion:</hi> in revenging our own wrongs, we never keep a mean, whereas in other mens (though much greater) the moſt intemperate will eaſily obſerve mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; Furthermore, the <hi>Heathens</hi> themſelves may teach us what <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Society,</hi> and what the <hi>Law of Nature</hi> requires of us in this caſe; when <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ciceron.</hi> lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3 <hi>Offic.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Natura ipſa praeſcribit, ut homo homini,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That Nature being the common Mother of Mankind preſcribes and ordains, that every Man endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and procures the good of another whatſoever he be, only becauſe he is a Man: Otherwiſe all bonds of ſociety, yea, and Mankind it ſelf muſt needs go to ruin:</hi> Therefore, as <hi>Juſtice</hi> is built on theſe two <hi>Baſes,</hi> or <hi>Pillars; firſt,</hi> that none
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48929:5"/>be wronged; and <hi>ſecondly,</hi> that good be done to all if it be poſſible; So alſo are there two ſorts of <hi>Injuſtice;</hi> the <hi>firſt,</hi> in thoſe who offer injury to their <hi>Neighbours:</hi> And the Second, in thoſe who when they have means to deliver the oppreſſed, do notwithſtanding ſuffer them to ſink under the burthen of their wrongs; Peradventure you will ſay, I fear in aiding the one, I ſhall do wrong to the other: But he that lays his hand on his heart, will find it is ſomewhat elſe, and not Juſtice that withholds him from their aſſiſtance. For as <hi>Cicero</hi> in another place obſerves, <hi>Either thou wilt not make the wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng doer thine Enemy, or not take pains, or not be at ſo much charge, or elſe negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, ſloth, or hindring of thine own occaſions, or the cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſing thy other deſigns, takes thee off from the defence of thoſe, whom otherwiſe thou art bound to relieve. Now in ſaying thou only attendeſt thine own affairs, fearing to wrong another, thou falleſt into another kind of injuſtice, for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u abandoneſt humane Society, in that thou wilt not afford any relief either of mind, body or goods, for the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsary Preſervation thereof.</hi> The <hi>Heathen Philoſophers</hi> and <hi>Politicians</hi> have Written more divinely hereof, than many of our modern Chriſtians. From hence alſo it proceeds, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Law ordains puniſhment to that Neighbour who will not deliver the Slave from the Outragious fury of his Maſter. Amongſt the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> if any man had ſeen another aſſaulted and diſtreſſed by <hi>Thieves</hi> and <hi>Robbers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diod. Si. cul. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. Ch. 2.</note> and did not according to his power preſently aſſiſt him, he was adjudged worthy of death, if at leaſt he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered or delivered not the Delinquents into the hands of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate: If he were remiſs in performing this duty, for the firſt <hi>Mulct,</hi> he was to receive a certain number of blows on his Body, and to faſt three days together. Likewiſe much upon the ſame reaſon is grounded that Law of this Nation, which amerces that Hundred where a Robbery or Murder is committed, and no care taken to apprehend the Offenders. Now, if the Neighbour be ſo firmly obliged (even by <hi>Heathen Laws</hi>) to ſuccour his diſtreſſed Neighbour, though unknown to him, when he is aſſaulted by Thieves: ſhall it not be much more lawful for a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Prince to aſſiſt, not <hi>Slaves</hi> againſt an Imperious <hi>Maſter,</hi> or <hi>Children</hi> againſt a furious <hi>Father;</hi> but pious <hi>Proteſtant Subjects,</hi> againſt an <hi>Idolatrous Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant?</hi> And if he careleſly or wilfully omit this duty;<note place="margin">Theucid. <hi>lib.</hi> 1.</note> deſerves he not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be eſteem'd an <hi>Offender,</hi> as well as the other a <hi>Robber,</hi> who neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to aſſiſt his Neighbour in that danger? <hi>Thucydides</hi> (lib. 1.) upon this ſubject writes, <hi>That theſe are not only Tyrants who make other men Slaves, but much more thoſe who having means to ſuppreſs and prevent ſuch op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, take no care to perform it.</hi> A <hi>Tyrant</hi> is in ſome meaſure compelled to hold a ſtraight hand over thoſe whom by violence and Tyranny he hath reduced; <hi>And to ſecure the Ills that he hath done by doing greater,</hi> becauſe as <hi>Tiberius</hi> ſaid, <hi>He holds the Wolf by the Ear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whom he can neither hold without pain and force, nor yet let go without Danger and Death.</hi> But he who with a negligent and idle regard looks on the outragiouſneſs of a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> and the Maſſacring of Innocents, whom he might have preſerved, like the Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſpectators of the <hi>Roman Sword-players,</hi> is ſo much more guilty than the <hi>Tyrant</hi> himſelf, by how much the Cruel and Homicidious directors and appointers of thoſe <hi>Bloody Sports,</hi> were more obnoxious than the poor and conſtrain'd <hi>Actors</hi> themſelves. If any object, that it is againſt reaſon and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity to meddle with anothers concerns,<note place="margin">Pompon. de Regi. Jur. Leg.</note> I anſwer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> did the <hi>Old Man</hi> in <hi>Terence; I am a Man, and I believe that all duties of humanity are fit and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for me:</hi> If others ſeeking to cover their Negligence and Baſeneſs, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that Bounds and Juriſdictions are diſtinguiſht one from another, and that it is not Lawful to thruſt ones <hi>Sickle</hi> into anothers <hi>Harveſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Neither am I alſo of that opinion, that it is Lawful upon any ſuch preſence to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craoch upon anothers Juriſdiction or Right or upon that occaſion to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurp</hi> anothers <hi>Countrey,</hi> as many have taken ſuch ſhadows to do,<note place="margin">Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. 2. Offic.</note> I would not (I ſay) that after the manner of thoſe <hi>Arbitrators</hi> whom <hi>Cicero</hi> ſpeaks of, thou Adjudge the things in controverſie to thy ſelf; I require only, that you repreſs the <hi>Prince</hi> who invades the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that you take
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48929:6"/>out the <hi>Serpents Sting,</hi> that you raiſe up a <hi>Church</hi> that lies groveling on the Ground as it were at her laſt Gaſp, that you ſtretch forth your hand of <hi>Compaſſion</hi> to an <hi>Afflicted People,</hi> and that you ſo diſcharge your ſelf of this duty, that all men may ſee your principal end was the <hi>Publick benefit</hi> of <hi>Humane ſociety,</hi> and not any private advantage of your own, which muſt ever give place to <hi>Publick Intereſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Briefly, to Epitomize what hath been formerly ſaid: If a <hi>Prince</hi> outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly ſurpaſs the bounds of Piety and Juſtice, a <hi>Neighbouring Prince</hi> may Juſtly and Religiouſly leave his own <hi>Country,</hi> not to <hi>Invade</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurp</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but to contain the other within the <hi>Limits</hi> of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Equity;</hi> Nay he is obliged in Honour and Conſcience ſo to do. If a <hi>Prince</hi> Tyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize over the People, a <hi>Neighour Prince</hi> ought to yield ſuccour as freely and willingly to the People, as he would do to the <hi>King</hi> his Brother, if the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple mutinied againſt him: If <hi>Porſenna</hi> brought <hi>Tarquinius Superbus</hi> back to <hi>Rome;</hi> much more juſtly might <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> requeſted by the <hi>Senate</hi> and <hi>Roman People,</hi> expel <hi>Maxentius</hi> the <hi>Tyrant</hi> from <hi>Rome.</hi> The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation due to this ſort of Courteſie hath wrought ſo ſtrange effects in the Hearts of many Princes, that ſome have received their profeſt Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; And others have fallen out with their deareſt friends, rather than Reſtore a Prince being fled unto them for ſuccour, when he was demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at their Hands; Some have been offerred great Rewards which have been offered for the Reſtitution of ſuch Exiles as lived within their Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories, others have entertain'd them with large yearly Penſions, and preſently aided them for the recovery of their Kingdoms; Some have given them whole Cities to dwell in, and others have been ſo forward in relieving ſuch as implored their help, that they have loſt their onw Kingdomes in defending them. But as the caſe now ſtands, nothing, can be a greater Security to us, than a League defenſive againſt the grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power of the Papiſt;<note place="margin">Du Hail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ian <hi>lib.</hi> 24</note> 
               <hi>Vis unitafortior.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Hiſtories</hi> of <hi>France</hi> it is written, that <hi>Charles</hi> the ſeventh having upon ſome diſpleaſure conceiv'd againſt the <hi>Dauphin,</hi> (who was his el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Son,) baniſh't him out of his Realm, and commanded that none of his Subjects harbour or receive him: The <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Burgundy</hi> (who was then <hi>Vaſſal</hi> to the <hi>French King,</hi> and mortal enemy to the <hi>Dauphin,</hi>) did nevertheleſs, not only receive him, but alſo gave him leave to chooſe what <hi>Caſtle, Hold,</hi> or <hi>City</hi> of his ſoever he pleaſed to dwell in, and ſent preſently <hi>Embaſſadors</hi> to his <hi>Father</hi> to make his excuſe for receiving him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Piero Mexias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. de Hen. 3.</note> in his Book of the <hi>Lives</hi> of the <hi>Roman Emperours,</hi> report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, That the <hi>Emperour Henry</hi> the <hi>third,</hi> (when as <hi>Peter King</hi> of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> was for his evil Government driven out of his Kingdom by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion of his own Subjects,) did not only receive and entertain him, but alſo reſtored him again to his own Kingdom; although the ſame <hi>Peter</hi> not long before had favoured the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> who Rebelled againſt the ſaid <hi>Emperour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> diſtruſting the protection of <hi>God</hi> flyeth to <hi>Achib King</hi> of <hi>Goth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Kings.</note> who giveth him <hi>Siglag</hi> to dwell in; And <hi>Jeroboam</hi> flying unto <hi>Shiſack King</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> was honourably received of him, and maintained there like a <hi>Prince,</hi> till <hi>Rehoboam</hi> being depoſed for his cruelty, he was ſent for out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and made <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Scots</hi> received <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth, flying from the perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth,<note place="margin">Holinſhed.</note> entertained him with a yearly Penſion, and aid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him for the Recovery of his Kingdom. <hi>Frederick King</hi> of <hi>Naples,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing oppreſſed by his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> fled unto the <hi>French King Lewis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Illeſcas. de Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andor. 6.</note> who received him with great Honour and Civility, made him <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Anjou,</hi> and gave him, 30000, <hi>Ducates</hi> of yearly Revenues.</p>
            <p>Now whether it be lawful and commendable thus to receive and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour another <hi>Prince</hi> who flyeth to him for Succour: If <hi>Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> deſerves more commendation, than <hi>Cruelty;</hi> If it be true what the <hi>Poet</hi> ſayeth <hi>Turpius ejicitur quam non Admittitur Hoſpes;</hi> If Princes were
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48929:6"/>firſt Ordained and Inſtituted to yield Relief to as many as were diſtreſſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If wiſer <hi>Princes</hi> have oftner received than rejcted them; And laſtly, if God moſt commonly <hi>Bleſſed</hi> them who yielded ſuch Relief, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe puniſhed thoſe who exerciſed no kind of <hi>Humanity</hi> towards them; Then this doubt is eaſily, and the difficulty quite taken away. <hi>Firſt,</hi> that <hi>Humanity</hi> which is incident to <hi>Men,</hi> is to be preferred before <hi>Cruelty,</hi> which is proper to <hi>Beaſts,</hi> no <hi>Man</hi> is ſo ſenſleſs as to doubt: <hi>Secondly,</hi> that the <hi>Wiſdome</hi> of thoſe <hi>Princes</hi> who have <hi>Har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our'd</hi> their <hi>Neighbours</hi> and <hi>Allies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">T. Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingh. in his Neuſtia.</note> is commended beyond all meaſure by the <hi>Writers</hi> who mention them; Whereas on the contrary, for thoſe <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhoſpitable Princes,</hi> all <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories</hi> ſhall ſooner periſh, then their <hi>Infamy</hi> be forgotten. And laſtly, all our <hi>Chronicles</hi> do ſufficiently teſtifie, how <hi>God Plagu'd</hi> the poſterity of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the fifth, for his extremity uſed to the poor diſtreſſed Prince of <hi>Scotland.</hi> And <hi>French Hiſtories</hi> do declare, that <hi>God</hi> never proſpered <hi>Lewis</hi> (Sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>Oultremer) King</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> becauſe he had dealt ſo unkindly with <hi>Richard Duke</hi> of <hi>Normandy</hi> an Infant, whom he had received into his Protection.</p>
            <p>Moreover, ſince it hereby appears, that every Prince ought to relieve his <hi>Royal Brother</hi> in diſtreſs, ſo much more readily ought he to afford <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour</hi> to a <hi>diſtreſſed People,</hi> by how much there is more juſt cauſe to pity many afflicted, than one alone. If a man becomes a <hi>Wolf</hi> to man, who hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that man (according to the Proverb) may not be inſtead of <hi>God</hi> to the needy? And therefore the <hi>Antients</hi> have reckon'd <hi>Hercules</hi> amongſt the <hi>Gods,</hi> becauſe he puniſh't and tam'd <hi>Procruſtes Buſiris,</hi> and other <hi>Tyrants,</hi> the <hi>Plagues</hi> of <hi>Mankind,</hi> and <hi>Monſters of the Earth.</hi> So whilſt the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> retained her freedom, ſhe was truly accounted the <hi>Safeguard</hi> of all the World againſt the violence of <hi>Tyrants,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Senate</hi> was the <hi>Port</hi> and <hi>Refuges</hi> of <hi>Kings, People</hi> and <hi>Nations.</hi> In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>Charlemain</hi> undertook to War againſt the <hi>Lombardy,</hi> being requeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to aſſiſt the Nobility of <hi>Italy,</hi> although the Kingdom of <hi>Lombards</hi> had been of a long continuance, and he had no juſt pretence of Right over them; Alſo when <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Bald King of France</hi> had Tyranically put to death the <hi>Governour</hi> of the <hi>Country</hi> between the River <hi>Soyne</hi> and <hi>Loyre,</hi> with <hi>Duke Lambert,</hi> and another Nobleman, called <hi>Jamitius,</hi> and divers others of the Nobility fled for fear to <hi>Lewis King</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> deſiring his Aid, it was there in full Aſſembly agreed, that <hi>Lewis</hi> ſhould wage War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Charles</hi> for the Re-eſtabliſhing in their Good, Honours, and Eſtates, thoſe whom he had unjuſtly diſpoſſeſt.</p>
            <p>Finally, as there hath ever been <hi>Tyrants</hi> diſperſt in all parts, ſo likewiſe all Hiſtories teſtifie that there hath been <hi>Neighbouring Princes</hi> to oppoſe <hi>Tyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi> and <hi>Maintain</hi> the <hi>People</hi> in their <hi>Rights.</hi> Wherefore that all <hi>Proteſtant Princes</hi> would at this time imitate ſo worthy Examples, by endevouring to ſuppreſs that <hi>French Tyrant,</hi> who ſo oppreſſes both Souls and Bodies, and the true Reformed Church of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Office; 1.36.</note> is the earneſt Prayers of all poor diſtreſſed <hi>French Proteſtants,</hi> and hearty deſires of all good Chriſtians: For <hi>he that repelleth not injuries from his fellow (if he be able) is in fault as he that offers it,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> Piety commands that the Law and Church of God be maintained: Juſtice requires that <hi>Tyrants</hi> and <hi>Deſtroyers of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind</hi> be compelled to reaſon: Charity Challenges the Right of Relieving and Reſtoring the oppreſſed.<note place="margin">De Bed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; par. 2.</note> Now thoſe that make no account of thoſe things, do (as much as in them lies) drive Piety, Juſtice, and Charity out of this World. It were to be wiſhed (ſaith <hi>Grotius</hi>) that many <hi>Princes</hi> and People at this day would take into conſideration that <hi>free</hi> and Pious Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ech of <hi>Fuelco Arch-biſhop</hi> once of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> Admoniſhing <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Simple,</hi> thus. <hi>Who may not be affraid, ſeeing you covet amity with the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of God, when to the Ruine and overthrow of the Chriſtian Name, you take unto you Pagan Arms, and enter into Leagues deteſtable? For there is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48929:7"/>little difference between aſsociating with Pagans, and worſhipping of Idols, as the Papiſts do.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.15.</note> 
               <hi>Be ye not therefore (ſaith St.</hi> Paul) <hi>unequally yoaked together with unbelievers; For what fellowſhip hath Righteouſneſs with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs? What communion hath Light with Darkneſs?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>And what Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord hath Chriſt with Belial? Or what part hath He that believeth with an Infidel?</hi> Nevertheleſs too too many Proteſtants have Eſpouſed and Leagued with the Popiſh Intereſt, whereby alone the <hi>French</hi> are now rendred thus formidable, In ſo much that (under God) nothing but a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſincere and Cordial League can retrieve the Reformed Religion: That as heretofore <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>third</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> So now <hi>Lewis</hi> the 14th. may be Ruined by that very League which he entred into for the Extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many there are (I am ſenſible) who raiſe a groundleſs fear and jealouſie amongſt us, as if, like <hi>Zophirus of Old,</hi> who by maiming himſelf and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiting the <hi>Renegado</hi> from <hi>Darius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n. li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2</note> was by that means admitted into <hi>Babylon,</hi> and ſo betrayed it to the Enemy. Theſe diſtreſſed <hi>French Hug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets</hi> ſhould come over with any ſuch deſign into this Nation: But theſe ſurmiſes, will ſeem very ridiculous, if we weigh all circumſtances con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them. As Firſt, the manner of their Arrival in ſuch ſmall Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels as none but men in greateſt extremity would hazard themſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lves in. Secondly what ſort of perſons they be that come over; whether they be not of all ſorts as well Women and Children, as Men? And whether they are not moſtly Men of profeſſions, as Fiſher-men, Clothiers, Weavers, and ſuch from whom we have more reaſon to expect advantage from their Trades, than danger from their Arms? Thirdly, whether there are not as manny arrived in <hi>Holland</hi> and other <hi>Proteſtant Countries</hi> as here, and whether the <hi>States</hi> have not the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Charity for their diſtreſs as we have? Fourthly, whether ſuch a conſpiracy (if ſo) could poſſibly be concea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed amongſt ſo many thouſands who are Arrived in all parts? Fifthly and laſtly, whether it ſtands not to reaſon that the ſame <hi>Popiſh Fury</hi> which baniſh them from <hi>France</hi> ſhould not as well to conceal their own Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p them from raiſing an outcry againſt <hi>Popery</hi> by their complaints, as to have them diſcountenanced and diſcredited where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'re they come. Likewiſe maliciouſly and out of deſign raiſe all theſe Calumnies and falſe Reports againſt them; So that there needs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> little of Argument to a think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Impartial Proteſtant</hi> to convince him of the reality of their ſufferings. And for the benefit that may accrue to the Nation, by their Planting themſelves amongſt us. He that reads ancient <hi>Hiſtories</hi> ſhall find that the <hi>Romans Hoſpitality</hi> to <hi>Strangers</hi> was the <hi>firſt ſtep</hi> of their <hi>greatneſs,</hi> and <hi>Corner Stone</hi> of that vaſt <hi>Empire.</hi> Thus whilſt <hi>Athens</hi> and <hi>Sparta</hi> (though for all other things endowed with moſt excellent Law.) yet upon their Nicity of <hi>admitting Strangers</hi> amongſt them, remained inconſiderable in the World as to power <hi>Rome</hi> in the mean while having her <hi>City thro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g'd</hi> with <hi>Inhabitants,</hi> from being <hi>Numerous,</hi> ſoon grew <hi>Potent, Creſeit interea Roma,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Livy.</note> 
               <hi>Albae Ruinis:</hi> the <hi>Ruin</hi> of <hi>Alba,</hi> was the <hi>Riſe</hi> of the <hi>Romans;</hi> and may the fall of <hi>France</hi> be the ſame to <hi>England.</hi> Never any <hi>State</hi> was ſo open to receive ſtrangers into their Body, as were the <hi>Romans,</hi> their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was to grant <hi>Naturalization,</hi> (which they call <hi>Jus Civitatis</hi> and to grant it in the <hi>Higheſt Degree,</hi> that is, not only <hi>Jus Commercii, Jus Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nubii, Jus Hereditatit,</hi> but alſo <hi>Jus ſuffragii, &amp; Jus Honorum;</hi> and this not to <hi>Singular Perſons</hi> alone, but likewiſe to <hi>whole Families;</hi> yea, to <hi>Cities,</hi> and ſometimes to <hi>Nations;</hi> And it ſorted with them accordingly; for <hi>winning</hi> as much of their <hi>generoſity,</hi> as <hi>Arms, Rome grew</hi> to be the <hi>Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan</hi> of the Univerſe. Now that <hi>England</hi> following the ſteps of Antient <hi>Rome</hi> in her <hi>Hoſpitality,</hi> may likewiſe imitate her in her Victories and Grandeur is the Hearty Prayers of, <hi>Philopatris.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
